RUSTAM ISANGULOV

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER | SOFTWARE ARCHITECT | PHD

PROFILE

Senior engineer with a strong interest in architecting and building software systems that help make better decisions, turn them into actions and bring measurable impact. Comfortable and experienced in delivering solutions that involve complex domain logic and mathematical modelling.

10+ years of experience in all aspects of software development life-cycle. Considerable experience working with diverse, cross-disciplinary (science, software, operations) engineering teams in the UK, USA and China.

Before 2013, I spent considerable time at an Industrial Research Lab (Cambridge, UK) as a senior research engineer delivering POCs for data processing, automation and machine reasoning projects.

EXPERIENCE

PRODUCT MANAGER, INTELLISENSE.IO, CAMBRIDGE UK - 2020-2021

Developed product roadmaps, feature specifications and requirements for the brains.app (an industrial SaaS AI platform); Managed effective product delivery by the "platform" scrum team (~12 engineers) to internal and external clients.

SOLUTIONS ANALYST, SCHLUMBERGER, BEIJING CHINA – 2018-2020

Performed analysis of automated planning needs for the well engineering platform (DrillPlan) and investigated potential applications of classical Al planning to improve consistency and procedural adherence.

PROJECT MANAGER, SCHLUMBERGER, HOUSTON USA - 2015-2018

Managed a team of ~12 engineers with the goal to deliver new decision management and execution system for drilling fluids workflows. On the technical side, I was responsible for multi-domain logical inference design to ensure the new product is well integrated with the drilling automation (see below) and a higher level workflow orchestration systems.

PROGRAM ARCHITECT, SCHLUMBERGER, HOUSTON USA – 2013-2015

Created the vision, defined technical direction and architecture, and guided technology stack choices for the drilling automation system that is now a part of the well-construction platform (DrillOps). Collaborated with ~30 engineers in the team to ensure a shared understanding of the vision and the plan-based automation architecture.

EDUCATION

Imperial College London, UK — PhD, Applied Mathematics

Moscow State Technological University "Stankin", Russia — Engineering Diploma (~MS), CAD/CAM Systems & Applied Mathematics

SKILLS

- Java 11 (OCP, May 2022) / JUnit 5 / Mockito / Maven / Spring
- C# / Matlab / C++ / SQL / Python
- Rational UML Modelling / Planning Domain Definition Language
- Git / GitHub / Aha! / Jira / Microsoft VSTS

PATENTS

- Systems and methods for executing a plan associated with multiple equipment by using rule-based inference (US11288609B2)
- Well Construction Management and Decision Support System (US10920565B2)
- Automated sliding drilling (US10883356B2)
- Method and system for directional drilling (US10612307B2)
- Method for calculating and displaying optimized drilling operating parameters and for characterizing drilling performance with respect to performance benchmarks (US10316653B2)

PUBLICATIONS

- Optimizing ROP through automation (Drilling Contractor, Sep 21 2011)
- Increased Rate of Penetration Through Automation (SPE-139897-MS)
- A mathematical model of an oil and gas field development process (European Journal of Applied Mathematics, Mar 8 2010)

CAMBRIDGE, UK

EMAIL: RUSTAM.ISANGULOV@ME.COM

LINKEDIN: WWW.LINKEDIN.COM/IN/RUSTAM-ISANGULOV